This video is sponsored by Proton Mail.
Magnetically levitating trains or magabs
are a concept we are all familiar with.
Sleek, frictionless with a top speed of
more than 500 km per hour. All the while
being more energy efficient than
conventional trains and less maintenance
intensive. A technological revolution
here to change transportation forever.
Or is it? It feels like everyone has
been talking about melas for decades
about how they are about to
revolutionize transportation guys any
moment now I swear but that moment just
doesn't seem to be coming. So what's
going on here? Are me leaves the future
or at least a viable form of
transportation? Or are they just another
[__] vaporware solving problems
nobody had while burning through
billions in taxpayers money? Let's take
a look. People have been experimenting
with magglevs for more than a century
now. The first ever maglev to gain any
real media attention was built in 1912
by French American Emil Bashalet. I'm
saying maglev, but it was more like a
small demonstrator. Bashalet even
helpfully strapped his daughter to it to
demonstrate its load capacity. Dad, is
this safe?
Let me just press the button.
He even got to exhibit his demonstrator
at the London Admiral where the concept
model went back and forth on a short
track levitating a centimeter above it.
Even Winston Churchill got to see it and
was quite impressed. Imagine what a head
trip it must have been to see an actual
levitating train in the 1910s. This
stuff would be kind of cool to look at
today. At the core, maglev technology is
not that complicated. It's quite simple
actually, but it's also one of those
simple in concept, hard in practice
kinds of things. Space rockets are very
simple machines in theory. Just put some
oxidizer on top of fuel in a tube, then
burn it in a way that it comes out in
the back. Boom, you're in space. except
it's actually really really difficult to
do and we've been trying to get it right
for a century and only now have we
gotten to the point that rockets are
only kind of [__] Similarly, mag
research has been going on for decades
and we have only recently gotten to the
point where the thing sort of works as
intended and historically there have
been many attempts to get it right which
we'll be discussing after the word from
today's sponsor Proton Mail. Proton Mail
is a privacy focused encrypted email
service keeping your personal data safe
from prying eyes owned by a nonprofit
organization based in Switzerland.
Proton was created by a team of CERN
scientists through a greatly successful
crowdfunding campaign and is now here to
safeguard your personal data and
correspondence. It is now as relevant as
ever since the Trump administration took
over US institutions and is basically
ignoring the rule of law. What's that?
You live outside the US? Well, have you
ever heard of section 702? It allows the
US government to monitor foreigners even
outside the US, but they also use it to
spy on US citizens. Surprise, surprise.
And they do all this without any
judicial oversight. No permit, no
warrant. So, it's best to keep your
private correspondence private. And
Proton Mail was made for exactly that in
mind, both for personal and business
use. I also use it as my personal
private email. No, you can't have it. If
you already have an email address at one
of the big providers, switching is easy
as you can set up Proton's auto
forwarding feature in just a few clicks.
Go to proton.me/adam
something to get started with Proton
Mail for free. Their service is always
free with optional paid subscription
plans for additional features and
benefits. That's proton.me/adam
something. Thank you for checking out
Proton Mail. At some point, everyone was
in on maglap tech, even the Soviets, who
built the most Soviet sci-fi looking
thing ever to exist. They envisioned it
as a sort of high-tech airport express,
though it never made it past the
prototype stage. Japan had built
numerous prototypes and smaller scale
systems like the Lineo line, originally
built for the 2005 Japan World Expo.
South Korea was also in on it, building
a small prototype system to serve the
1993 Tun Expo and later a whole new line
to Sin in Chon airport. Germany had been
heavily involved in development
constructing several smaller lower speed
systems eventually culminating in the
transrapid. Massive plans were made.
Multiple transpid lines were proposed
across Germany. Chief among them Berlin
Hamburg bridging the divide between
former east and west by the power of
technology. Also a magv line from
Munich's main railway station to Munich
airport. A project described in the
legendary maglev or maglev speech by
Edmund Stoyber the then minister
president of Bavaria. In his own words,
if you from the main railway station in
Munich with 10 minutes without having to
check in at the airport, then you
basically start at the airport at you
start your flight at the main railway
station in Munich. 10 minutes. Take a
look at the big airports. If you are at
Heathrow in London or somewhere else my
shard uh in France or in ah in in ah in
Rome. If you look at the distances if
you look at Frankfurt you'll realize
that 10 minutes you may easily need to
find your gate in Frankfurt. When you
start from the flight from from the main
station you board the main station you
take the transpid to the airport in 10
minutes in to France airport. Then you
basically start here at Munich Central
Station. Of course, this means that the
main station is basically closer to
Bavaria. It is growing onto the Bavarian
cities because it's obvious because many
lines from Bavaria converge at the main
station. This speech is kind of a meme
in Germany. And I'm happy to have
contributed to your cultural education.
Just for the sake of perspective, by the
way, the same politicians who were
pushing the trans rapid in Germany were
also busy in the meantime gutting and
defunding German rail, resulting in its
disastrous state. Today, China had also
been deeply involved in maglev tech,
including with Germany's transpid
technology, constructing a number of
systems like the Chunka Maglev to
Chungcha airport or the Shanghai maglev
to Shanghai airport. So, I guess Chinese
people could board their own main
railway station unlike Germans. Britain
also tried getting in on the fun with
whatever the hell this was. When looking
at these projects, you might notice
certain commonalities, like the majority
having been built to serve airports and
world expose. Now, if you hear the
expression transit project together with
airport or expo, you do well to be
suspicious. An alarm bell should go off
in your head because there is a risk
that you are about to be sold a gadget
bond. Gadget bonds are high-tech
transportation systems that will
revolutionize the way we travel. They
are a technological breakthrough that
will change our world forever. And then
one gets built and it turns out to be a
shittier version of the transit we
already have. Right? And expose and
airports are a prime territory where
such transit usually manifests. And I
believe magabs belong to the gadget bunk
category. They are highly proprietary
meaning its system cannot combine with
your pre-existing infrastructure. In
case of problems you can't reroute a
conventional train onto magab tracks and
vice versa. Having magabs means you now
need a whole other parallel
infrastructure network. Also magabs use
cases are very limited. If you want your
maglap system to make sense instead of
conventional highspeed rail, you're
basically stuck with distance single
points in a more or less straight line.
Serving local traffic is out of the
question since that way you will never
even reach a fraction of your top speed.
What's the point of having a magab then?
And yes, there are local magab lines,
but every single one of those could have
been a conventional line without
affecting quality of service. Mag Labs
are like VR. Basically, a very
specialized and high-tech gadget that's
very good at certain things and near
unusable for others. Try playing with
continuous movement in Halflife Alex.
You'll be throwing up after 5 minutes.
But how can I be so quick to write off
the technology? Japan is building a
brand new maglev line right now, the Chu
Shinkansen, which will enter service in
just a few years. Meanwhile, Shanghai
has its famous operational magv line
whizzing passengers at 430 km/h. Not so
fast. Literally, the Shanghai Mag Lab is
the only appreciable high-speed magab
line we have on the planet right now. In
regular operation, that is. And by that,
I mean a line longer than just a few
kilometers which regularly achieves high
speeds in everyday operation. And it's
complete [__] The line is impractical
as it doesn't go all the way to the
center, meaning you have to change
trains halfway. All the while, there is
a direct metro connection duplicating
its route, which actually takes you to
the center directly. operation is
horribly expensive and that famed speed
of 430 kilometers per hour had since
been reduced to 300. And even when it
operated at full speed, it was only
reached on a short section in the
middle. You could get distracted for a
minute and miss it. The whole line is 30
km long, which the train covers in about
8 minutes. It's basically just a tourist
attraction right now with no real use to
the city of Shanghai. And it's even kind
of bad at being a tourist attraction.
People who took it talk about the trains
looking dated since they haven't been
overhauled in a quarter of a century.
Also, 300 km/h is just not that big of a
deal anymore. In an era where
conventional highspeed trains can reach
350. Oh, but look, China is still
investing in mag labs and they have a
whole new prototype to test at very high
speeds. Yeah. Yeah, they do. They're
hedging their bets. There are lots of
potential avenues for innovation and
competition, and you never know which
one will go big. So, you invest in
multiple and see what happens. Magv
development is just one of the many
irons the Chinese are keeping in the
fire just in case. Ah, but the Japanese
are building their own magv line now.
The Chi Shinkansen, a 438 km long
intercity magv line, whisking passengers
at 500 km/h. Well, in about a decade on
the first segment, with the construction
having already gone on for a decade now.
Then once the first segment is done in a
decade, you'll have to wait another
decade for the second segment. If all
goes well, costing between 60 and $70
billion in 2025 before the Trump
hyperinflation. The Chu Shinkansen
illustrates the problem with melabs
rather well. Past a point, a project
will just take too long to build for too
much money for relatively little
benefit. Decades of construction, tens
of billions of dollars, so you can get
from Tokyo to Nagagoya 45 minutes
faster. But you also need to first get
to Shinagaba station in Tokyo as opposed
to going straight from central station.
So building this proprietary, extremely
lengthy and expensive project might not
make a whole lot of sense after all.
Compare the Chu Shinkansen to the
original Tokaido Shinkansen which
replaced the old Tokaido line between
Tokyo and Naguya. The Japanese diet
approved the plans in 1958 and 6 years
later they already had the first segment
up and running with the entire Tokaido
Shinkansen ending up costing about 12.5
billion or about 16th of the Jinkansen.
The original Tokyo Shinkansen cut down
travel times between Tokyo and Naguya
from about 6 hours to three and later
upgrades to tracks and rolling stock
have once again held that with the
current fastest connection being 1 hour
27 minutes. And it's nice that the new
maglev could have even that but the
shorter the travel time you're having
the smaller your savings are. So the
original Shinkansen compared to the old
conventional rail is a saving of 3 hours
for 12.5 billion while the magab is a
saving of 45 minutes for 60 to 70
billion. rather it will be once the
multi-deade long construction finishes.
Guys, this this whole Chu Shinkansen
line could have been a [__]
conventional high-speed rail line at 350
km/h. So, MagLab as a technology works
and it might make some sense in some
limited contexts on paper, but in
practice, not really. Conventional
highspeed rail has gotten to the point
where it can reliably compete with
MagLab trains with their new standard
max speed of 350 km/h. It's still slower
than the MagLab's 500 km/h top speed,
but in exchange, you get a system that
is interoperable with your existing
network. There is already a ton of
expertise and production capacities to
build and run the thing. And this
somewhat lower speed also means that you
can make more stops on the way and serve
a lot more people at the cost of a few
tens of minutes. Also, CO has shown us
that we don't need to be physically
everywhere all the time. So, a Japanese
executive could rush to a meeting from
Tokyo to Nagua in about 40 minutes on
the brand new $70 billion mega line. or
he can just do a zoom call from his
bedroom. So basically, maglands are a
hyper advanced mode of transportation
that are very good at one thing, speed,
but are lacking in basically all other
aspects compared to conventional
highspeed rail, which is a far more
balanced mix of benefits. And it's also
a question whether we need to be able to
get everywhere that quickly to begin
with versus just firing up zoom or
something. My answer to that question is
no. And for all these reasons, I
consider magg Labs to be gadget bonds.
Unless we figured out ultra cheap high
temperature superconductors or
something, let's just stick with
conventional highspeed rail.
[Music]